Guide to the John Nolen Papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
Nolen, John papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
- Series IV. Professional Career
  - Landscape Architect and City Planner
    - Project Material
      - Correspondence
        - Roadside Improvement, 1930 (Box 75, Folder 30)
          Correspondence - financing of "Roadside Improvement" project; Julius Rosenwald Fund
        - Riverton, New Jersey, 1929 - 1931 (Box 75, Folder 31)
          Correspondence - proposed zoning ordinance for Riverton
        - Richmond, Virginia, 1914 - 1924 (Box 75, Folder 32)
          Correspondence, newspaper clipping; postcards - city planning for Richmond; zoning ordinance
        - Reading Case - Legal, 1925 - 1928 (Box 75, Folder 33)
          Correspondence, reports - claim against Arthur K. Reading for unsettled payments related to development plans for Belmont-on-the-Gulf in Florida
        - Raleigh, North Carolina State School for the Blind and Deaf, 1920 - 1922 (Box 75, Folder 34)
          Correspondence - claim against School for the Blind and Deaf for unsettled payments
        - Raleigh, North Carolina State School for the Blind and Deaf, 1917 - 1920 (Box 75, Folder 35)
          Correspondence - landscape work for site of new School for the Blind and Deaf
        - Professional Practice and Charges, 1924 - 1928 (Box 75, Folder 38)
          Correspondence, reports, newspaper clipping
        - Professional Practice and Charges, 1922 - 1924 (Box 75, Folder 39)
          Correspondence, reports; American Society of Landscape Architects booklets "By Laws" and "Twenty Fifth Annual Meeting"
        - Professional Practice and Charges, 1919 - 1922 (Box 75, Folder 40)
          Correspondence, reports
        - Point Loma Estates, 1925 - 1932 (Box 75, Folder 41)
          Correspondence, photographs - planning work for Point Loma Estates in San Diego, CA; unpaid bills for services rendered
        - Prescott, Charles J., 1926 (Box 75, Folder 42)
          Correspondence - landscape work and swimming pool for Prescott's property in Norwood, MA
        - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1919 - 1924 (Box 75, Folder 44)
          Correspondence, notecards, newspaper clippings, pamphlets - city planning for Pittsburgh; housing; Pittsburgh Citizen's Committee on a City Plan
        - Pettengill Park, 1923 (Box 75, Folder 45)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings - planning work for Pettengill Park in Lewiston, ME
        - Sacramento, California, 1914 (Box 75, Folder 46)
          Notebooks, loose notecards, pamphlets
        - Fancy, C.B., 1923 (Box 76, Folder 1)
          Correspondence with C.B. Fancy of Rochester, NY - specialized job prospects, worked on Mariemont project
        - Filene, E.A., 1918 - 1923 (Box 76, Folder 2)
          Correspondence with E.A. Filene, President of William Filene's Sons Co., Boston - Boston Liberal Group; civic concerns; Mr. Van Ness H. Bates
        - Foster, Philip W., 1925 - 1931 (Box 76, Folder 3)
          Correspondence - ending of Florida partnership
        - Geddes, Patrick, 1922 - 1923 (Box 76, Folder 4)
          Correspondence with Geddes, Lewis Mumford, Liberty Hyde Bailey, James Sturgis Pray, Russell Sage Foundation - Geddes proposed visit to U.S.
        - Griggs, E.H., 1918 - 1923 (Box 76, Folder 5)
          Correspondence - Grigg's lecture series, personal and professional matters
        - Sharon, Massachusetts, 1927 - 1930 (Box 76, Folder 6)
          Correspondence, reports - reconnaissance survey of Sharon; garden suburbs
        - Smith's Agricultural School, 1908 - 1921 (Box 76, Folder 7)
          Correspondence, photographs - campus planning for agricultural school in Northhampton, MA; Booklet "Last Will and Testament of Oliver Smith,, Esq."
        - Smith College (Box 76, Folder 8)
          Contents of folder moved on 8/2/78 to #2903, Box 36, Smith College folder
        - Hamilton, Ohio, 1918 - 1919 (Box 76, Folder 9)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings - city planning for Hamilton
        - Sioux City, Iowa, 1930 - 1932 (Box 76, Folder 10)
          Correspondence, reports - city planning and comprehensive throughfare plan for Sioux City
        - Stamford, Connecticut, 1927 - 1928 (Box 76, Folder 11)
          Correspondence, pamphlets - plan for subdivison near Stamford for Stamford Development Co.
        - Spartanburg, South Carolina, 1922 - 1936 (Box 76, Folder 12)
          Correspondence, pamphlets - city planning for Spartanburg
        - Spartanburg, South Carolina, 1920 - 1921 (Box 76, Folder 13)
          Correspondence - city planning for Spartanburg
        - Stamford, Connecticut, 1928 - 1929 (Box 76, Folder 14)
          Correspondence - plan for subdivision near Stamford for Stamford Development Co.
        - Hoggson, W.J., 1913 - 1918 (Box 76, Folder 15)
          Correspondence - need for civic improvements in Greenwich, CT; development of Beech Nut Corp. plant; industrial housing
        - Hoosac Cotton Mills - North Adams, MA, 1921 (Box 76, Folder 16)
          Correspondence, blueprint - planning for North Adams; property improvements for Cotton Mill; industrial housing
        - International Mill & Timber Company - Bay City, MI, 1916 - 1917 (Box 76, Folder 17)
          Correspondence - Sterling ready cut houses, industrial housing
        - Ingersoll, C.H., 1916 - 1917 (Box 76, Folder 19)
          Correspondence - methods for house building; low cost housing; housing for Waterbury; housing for South Orange; Commonwealth Club
        - International Coal Products Corporation, 1918 - 1920 (Box 76, Folder 20)
          Correspondence - plan for town center, Clinchfield, VA
        - Jacksonville, Florida, 1922 - 1928 (Box 76, Folder 21)
          Correspondence, brochure - city planning for Jacksonville
        - Johnson City, Tennessee, 1927 - 1930 (Box 76, Folder 22)
          Correspondence - city planning for Johnson City
        - Juanita Valley Realty Corporation, 1924 (Box 76, Folder 23)
          Correspondence - subdivision development in Mount Union, PA; United States Refractories Corporation; Mr. Bendelow of Chicago, golf architect
        - Kenosha, Wisconsin, 1916 (Box 76, Folder 24)
          Correspondence - housing survey for Kenosha; Kenosha House Building Company; Manufactures' Association of Kenosha; housing in Hopedale, MA
        - Lake Wales, Florida, 1922 - 1925 (Box 76, Folder 25)
          Correspondence, pamphlet - planning of Mammoth Grove, near Lake Wales; Florida Highland Citrus Corporation
        - Lake Wales, Florida, 1926 (Box 76, Folder 26)
          Correspondence, pamphlets, maps, blueprint - planning of Mammoth Grove, near Lake Wales; Florida Highland Citrus Corporation; Lake Wales City Planning and Zoning Commission
        - Kansas City, Kansas, 1915 - 1918 (Box 76, Folder 28)
          Correspondence, map, speech - city planning for Kansas City; J.C. Nichols; John Nolen speech abstract "Business Advantages of City Planning"
        - Lake Wales, Florida, 1927 - 1928 (Box 76, Folder 31)
          Correspondence - city planning for Lake Wales
        - LaMonte, Miss C.B., 1912 - 1921 (Box 76, Folder 32)
          Correspondence, pamphlet - housing plan for Westerly Gardens, Bound Brook, NJ; "The Evergreens"
        - Lansing, Michigan, 1915 - 1920 (Box 76, Folder 33)
          Correspondence - city planning for Lansing
        - Lee, G.W., 1920 - 1921 (Box 76, Folder 34)
          Correspondence with George Winthrop Lee, newspaper clippings, bulletins - Cooperative country living; restorative powers of art; Engineers Club; Boston Public Library
        - Latham, J.E. - Greensboro, North Carolina, 1915 - 1918 (Box 76, Folder 35)
          Correspondence with J.E. Latham of J.E. Latham Co., cotton merchants - development of housing subdivision in Greensboro
        - Leominster, Massachusetts, 1927 (Box 76, Folder 36)
          Correspondence - development of property in Leominster for recreational use; town planning; V.W. Doyle, Mayor; Grosvenor Plowman
        - Lewis, Nelson P., 1922 (Box 76, Folder 37)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings - Nelson P. Lewis, planning engineer for NYC Board of Estimates, Boston planning consultant
        - Lexington, Massachusetts, 1922 - 1931 (Box 76, Folder 38)
          Correspondene - comprehensive plan for Lexington
        - Lincoln, Massachusetts, 1916 (Box 76, Folder 39)
          Correspondence - plan for Lincoln School Playground
        - Lincoln, Nebraska, 1911 - 1912 (Box 76, Folder 40)
          Correspondence - comprehensive plan for Lincoln
        - Lock Haven, Pennsylvania, 1912 - 1917 (Box 76, Folder 41)
          Correspondence - comprehensive plan for Lock Haven, including development of recreational space
        - Wisconsin State Capitol, 1910 - 1912 (Box 77, Folder 2)
          Correspondence - landscape work for grounds of new Wisconsin State Capitol building; tree list
        - Miscellaneous, 1922 - 1930 (Box 77, Folder 3)
          Correspondence, pamphlets - requests for and receipt of articles, books, and other information pertaining to city planning, landscape architecture, and related topics; Massachusetts Civic League; Garden Club of Bedfordm, MA; National Conference on City Planning; Jacob L. Crane, planner and landscape architect; Kingsport, TN; E.L. Lindeman, NY School of Social Work; Rudolf Ungewitter thesis topic, Pontiac or Flint, MI; U.S. Chamber of Commerce and city planning; Boston planning; American Institute of Consulting Engineers; The Cambridge School, Summer School; Stamford, CT and zoning plan; professional ethics for city planners; Passiac, NJ and Technical Advisory Corporation; American Federation of the Arts; informal reviews of books, articles, reports; Richard T. Ely; Benton MacKaye; traffic concerns; Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Company; Nolen's club memberships; landscape architecture contracts and specifications general info; Town Planning Institute of Canada; Baron G. Collier, real estate developer; Palos Verdes Estates; International Town Planning Conference; U.S. ports; Nolen's writings
        - Wisconsin State Capitol, 1911 - 1935 (Box 77, Folder 4)
          Correspondence, speech - planning work for State Capitol grounds including planting list; city planning for madison; plans for grounds of Arboretum; Address by John Nolen at dedication of the Arboretum and Wild Life Refuge of the University of Wisconsin, Madison on July 17, 1934
        - Lockport, NY, 1917 - 1920 (Box 77, Folder 5)
          Correspondence, pamphlet, map - housing problem in Lockport; city planning Annual Report, Lockport Homes Company, Inc.
        - London, Ontario, 1919 - 1920 (Box 77, Folder 6)
          Correspondence, report - comprehensive city plan for London
        - Longwood Improvement Association, 1913 - 1914 (Box 77, Folder 7)
          Correspondence, photographs - street extensions, and other improvements in Armory playground neighborhood of Brookline, MA
        - Lowell, Massachusetts, 1922 - 1923 (Box 77, Folder 8)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings - city planning for Lowell
        - Lowell, Massachusetts, 1922 - 1928 (Box 77, Folder 9)
          Correspondence, map, photograph - city planning for Lowell
        - Lower Marion Township, Pennsylvania, 1921 - 1922 (Box 77, Folder 10)
          Correspondence - development of Township property for playground and buildings, Y.M.C.A.
        - Lower Marion Township, Pennsylvania, 1921 - 1922 (Box 77, Folder 11)
          Correspondence - zoning and planning for Township
        - Lynn, Massachusetts, 1914 (Box 77, Folder 12)
          Correspondence, reports, speech - background information on Lynn; City Planning Address by John Nolen, Delivered at Lynn, MA, 29 May 1914
        - Lynch, W.G., 1918 - 1920 (Box 77, Folder 13)
          Correspondence with W.G. Lynch of W.G. Lynch Company, designers and builders of industrial housing in Waterbury, CT
        - Lynchburg, Virginia, 1907 - 1919 (Box 77, Folder 14)
          Correspondence, pamphlets - city planning for Lynchburg
        - Lynn, Massachusetts, 1921 - 1925 (Box 77, Folder 15)
          Correspondence - city planning for Lynn
        - MacArthur, A. - Binghampton, NY, 1927 - 1933 (Box 77, Folder 16)
          Correspondence - development of MacArthur's property in Binghampton; city planning for Binghampton
        - MacArthur, A. - Binghampton, NY, 1920 - 1924 (Box 77, Folder 17)
        - Macon, Georgia, 1922 - 1925 (Box 77, Folder 18)
          Correspondence - city planning and zoning for Macon
        - Manchester, New Hampshire, 1923 - 1924 (Box 77, Folder 19)
          Correspondence - city planning and zoning for Manchester
        - Marion, Indiana, 1919 - 1920 (Box 77, Folder 20)
          Correspondence - city planning for Marion
        - Massachusetts Bay Celebration, 1927 - 1930 (Box 77, Folder 22)
          Correspondence, bulletin, newspaper clippings - Massachusetts Bay Tercentenary of 1930; New England Newsletter, April 1929
        - Massachusetts Civic League, 1923 - 1937 (Box 77, Folder 23)
          Correspondence, pamphlets - Committee on Housing and Town Planning; "The Lens," bulletin of Massachusetts Civic League; "Politics and Corruption in American Cities - A New Theory," E.S. Griffith
        - Maximo Estates, 1924 - 1926 (Box 77, Folder 24)
          Correspondence - subdivision plan, Maximo Estates, for Ingoldsby & McCutcheon, Realtors, St. Petersburg, FL
        - Maxwell, George H., 1918 - 1933 (Box 77, Folder 25)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets - George H. Maxwell, Executive Director of National Reclamation Association and of American Homecroft Society; housing
        - McKeesport, Pennsylvania, 1930 (Box 77, Folder 26)
          Correspondence, bulletins - city planning and zoning for McKeesport, "The Champer of Commerce Record: Bulletin for the McKeesport Chamber of Commerce"
        - Meinig, E. Richard - Oakbrook, 1923 - 1927 (Box 77, Folder 27)
          Correspondence - development plans for E. Richard Meinig's property, Oakbrook in Reading, PA; The Richard Meinig Co., clothing manufacturer, of Reading, PA; Reading City Planning Commission's opposition to row house design
        - Meinig, E. Richard - Oakbrook, 1927 - 1928 (Box 77, Folder 28)
          Correspondence - development plans for E. Richard Meinig's property, Oakbrook in Reading, PA; The Richard Meinig Co., clothing manufacturer, of Reading, PA
        - Middletown, Ohio, 1918 - 1920 (Box 77, Folder 29)
          Correspondence - survey of Middletown; city planning; property development; Lawrence Veiller's work in Middletown; federal and industrial housing
        - Milton, Pennsylvania, 1918 (Box 77, Folder 32)
          Correspondence, reports - housing and community development for Milton; "Milton, PA - Survey of Social Conditions" by Marguerite Walker Jordan for John Nolen
        - Middleton, Connecticut, 1917 (Box 77, Folder 33)
          Correspondence - plan for workers housing for Russell Manufacturing Co. in Middletown
        - Miscellaneous, 1925 - 1928 (Box 77, Folder 34)
          Correspondence, pamphlets - Woodstock, VT; development of Kingsport, TN; Palos Verdes Estates and art appreciation; William and Mary College; membership in Authors' League of America; Walter Channing and Palm Hammock development
        - Miscellaneous, 1929 (Box 77, Folder 35)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets - requests for and receipt of articles, books, and other information pertaining to city planning, landscape architecture and related topics; foot subways (underground street crossings); Beaux-Arts Institute of Design, Warren Prize; city planning and children; airport planning; summer homes in NH; National Council for Protection of Roadside Beauty; Rudolf Ungewitter thesis topic, Pontiac or Flint, MI; village planning for Suffren, NY; city planning laws and zoning enabling acts for Pennsylvania; Philadelphia city planning; use of Nolen's San Diego plan for Antwerp Exhibition; The Art of Seeing training school in Brookline, MA; American Academy in Rome Landscape Architecture Fellowship; Fritz Malcher and street traffic reform; The Milton Fund for Research;; Robert M. Sawyer and Division of Community Planning; Chamber of Commerce of the U.S.; housing; recreational spaces
        - Miscellaneous, 1930 (Box 77, Folder 36)
          Correspondence - requests for and receipt of articles, books, and other information pertaining to city planning, landscape architecture and related topics; U.S. Department of Commerce; John M. Edy's appointment as City Manager for Flint, MI; city planning for Little Rock, AR; metropolitan Boston; Miami Building Permits for 1928-29 and Clearing House Report for 1929; state planning for Ohio; Edith Elmer Wood and status of Nolen's new towns; planning in New Jersey; Robert A. Ware; Vermont; airport planning; roadside improvement; Chicago Regional Planning Association; National Educational Conference, New York University; establishment of smoke inspection department in MA; Minutes of Housing Comittee, Boston, Jan. 1930; Professor Rudolph Weaver, University of Florida; Jacob L. Crane; "Opportunity of a Century" for Boston by Robert Sawyer Jigger, architect; Dallas County, TX Better Town Contest; Rudolph Weaver; civic improvement; Charles Henry Cheney, Palos Verdes Estates; unemployment situation in Ohio; Warren H. Manning
        - Miscellaneous, 1930 (Box 77, Folder 37)
          Correspondence, pamphlets - requests for and receipt of articles, books, and other information pertaining to city planning, landscape architecture and related topics; designs of street crossings; planning municipal development; Harvard City Planning School; Olmsted Brothers and public parks; housing in Ohio; company towns; New England Association of America; National Joint Committee on Municipal Reporting; City Planning article by Robbins B. Stoeckel; American Physical Education Association; planning in New Jersey; Jacob L. Crane and zoning; Charles H. Diggs, Regional Planning Commission; The Art of Seeing technical school in Brookline, MA; Chicago Plan Commission and elevated superhighways; city planning in big cities; Engineering Socities of Boston; U.S. Dept of Agriculture, Forest Service; housing; North Carolina; The New Republic; Dept of Commerce and subdivision regulations; planning school programs; people connected to planning of Niagara Frontier Region; city and regional planning studies and mosaic maps; Hoover Commission on Home Ownership; city planning work in Kansas; Malcom F. Waring, landscape and planning work; Horace M. Albright, Director of Dept. of Interior, National Park Service, and Yellowstone Park; H. Maier, architect, and coloring cement; The Architects' Small House Service Bureau; F. J. Mulvihill planning work in Pennsylvania; Karl B. Lohman and proposed book on city planning;U.S. Dept. of Commerce zoning and city planning publications; E.P Goodrich and housing; The New York Times; study of long term budgeting and capital expenditures connected to city planning program; home builders and home design
        - Miscellaneous, 1931 (Box 77, Folder 38)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets - requests for and receipt of articles, books, and other information pertaining to city planning, landscape architecture and related topics; American Federation of Arts; establishment of Los Angeles Housing Committee; zoning ordinances for municipalities; forestry in Los Angeles; The Inquiry and conferences; Professor John H. Eisenhauer and Romance and Reality; Henry G. Morse and development for Essex Fells, NY; Phillip Martindale, U.S. Ranger Naturalist Service and lecture tour; Jacob L. Crane and potential meeting;Coleman Woodbury of Institute for Economic Research and land takings in MA; General Federation of Women's Clubs and community planning; Clarence S. Stein and Conference on Regional Planning in Virginia; School of Horticulture for Women and possibilities of employment for graduates; Massachusetts Forestry Association and conservation efforts; aerial photographs; industrial development; U.S. Chamber of Commerce and planning commissions in U.S.; Chicago Regional Planning Association meeting and conference; Henry Wright and Forum article; Olmsted Brothers, public parks and playgrounds
        - Miscellaneous, 1932 - 1935 (Box 77, Folder 39)
          Correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets - requests for and receipt of articles, books, and other information pertaining to city planning, landscape architecture and related topics; recommendation of Arthur W. Gilbert for post of Commissioner of Agriculture; C.A. Dykstra, Cincinnati, 'Future of American Cities;' The Massachusetts Society of Washington D.C.; Tenth National Shade Tree Conference; U.S. Dept. of Agriculture reports; Russell A. Holy thesis; subdivision plan for Henry D. Green property in Reading, PA; introduction of Mr. Manne Carlman, Swedish architect; Anniversary Celebration of Amalgamated Dwellings in NYC; Jimmie Mattern, Round-World Flier; 'Why Omit Housing in City Planning' address by Francis J. Mulvihill; Anton A. Pruckner, landscape and garden lighting; F.C. Pickron, questions about engineer profession; Dept. of Commerce, zoned municipalities; meeting of Ford Fall Folks; Eastern Steamship Lines refund; development scheme for Harry Ryrie's property near Oakville, Ontario; A.E. Howland, Chief Engineer of Long Island State Park Commission, parkway construction; Benton McKaye, Regional Planning Association of America; The Trustees of Public Reservations; John A. Storm, professional advice; William H. Douglass, planning in Phoenix, AZ; The Vicking Press; Clarence S. Stein; Boston city planning; The Heliotype Company; Arts Weekly; Herbert L. Russell, Detroit planning; Yellow Cab Co., excessive rates; Fritz Malcher, divided roadway for parkways; Conifer Society of America; New Year's Greeting card from Fay, Spofford, & Thorndike, Engineers
        - Reading Clippings, 1920 (Box 88, Folder 2)
          City planning in Reading, PA
        - San Diego, 1920, 1929 (Box 88, Folder 3)
          Correspondence with George W. Marston related to results of planning in San Diego; Correspondence, news clippings, reports related to Torrey Pines
        - Wyomissing Park, 1919, 1927 (Box 88, Folder 8)
          2 brochures
        - Report on Civic Survey and Preliminary Plan for Flint, Michigan, 1918 (Box 88, Folder 10)
          By John Nolen
        - Scrapbook - San Diego, California, 1924 - 1927 (Box 88)
          Binder. Newspaper Clippings - City planning, zoning, harbor improvement, civic center
        - Reading Regional Plan, 1931 - 1932 (Box 88)
          Binder. Office Record - Personnel, Reports, Contract (Finances), Survey, Population Charts, Promotion
        - Reading Times (Pennsylvania), 1931 - 1932 (Box 89, Folder 1)
          Newspaper clippings; Brochure - planning, industry, local issues
        - Reading Pennsylvania - Clippings, 1931 - 1932 (Box 89, Folder 2)
          Planning, industry, local and statewide issues
        - Reading, Pennsylvania, 1908 - 1911 (Box 89, Folder 3)
          Newspaper clippings and notes related to local planning issues; Plan of Athletic Field Boys' High School; Program for the 16th Annual Convention of the League of Cities of the Third Class in Reading; Brochure for The Hotel Reading; 36th Annual Report of the Board of Health; Reading Trolley Guide; Blueprint of Geo. F. Baer's property in 15th Ward; "The Awakening of Reading" by Herbert R. Green
        - Flint, Michigan, 1922 - 1925 (Box 89, Folder 4)
          Correspondence - planning, zoning
        - Flint, Michigan - Flint City Planning Board, 1920 - 1921 (Box 89, Folder 5)
          Correspondence and reports
        - Flint Board of Education, 1921 - 1923 (Box 89, Folder 6)
          Correspondence, clippings - location of school sites